<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2007 University of Oxford

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>The Importance of Supporting Community Roles</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>Although tools are an important part of a development environment they are not what makes a
      project successful. The support of a variety of important roles within a project is what
      really counts. Broadly speaking these roles are:</p>

    <ul>
      <li><strong>User</strong> - someone who is trying to fill a need by adopting the outputs of a
        project. Directly involving the users in a project helps to ensure that it does what is
        intended. By providing user focussed documentation, support and bug/feature tracking users
        can be directly involved with the project.</li>

      <li><strong>Developer</strong> - someone who started life as a user, but has found the need to
        contribute to the project in the form of documentation, user support or code patches (in the
        case of a software project). Developers may also contribute by assisting with the design of
        solutions to bugs and implementations of feature requests.</li>

      <li><strong>Committer</strong> - someone who has been active as a developer for some time and
        has been recognised by the community as being a valuable member of the project team. They
        have the ability to directly contribute to the project by editing the source files for
        published documentation and software products.</li>

      <li><strong>Programme Management Committee Member</strong> - someone who is responsible for
        the strategic objectives of the project. The PMC steers the project on behalf of the
        community and attempts to ensure a unified vision is available to all.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>Any set of tools adopted by a project must be adopted in order to facilitate these different
      roles. For example, users need access to clear and accurate documentation. Whilst a wiki may
      be attractive from the point of view of easy editing, is it really the best tool for your
      users? Perhaps you should be using a wiki for your developers, but have an editing and
      publishing cycle for your users docs.</p>

    <p>Another important consideration when selecting your project's supporting tools is their
      ability to facilitate communication between the different project roles. In an open
      development community it is important that all members of the community, from user onwards,
      feel that they have some influence on the project. If users do not feel that they have an
      audible voice they will not become developers on your project. Without developers your
      committer base will dry up. Without committers you are unlikely to be able to form a
      functioning Project Management Committee.</p>

    <p>The diagram below illustrates what tools and what resources are required by each of the
      roles. It should be noted that each role with increasingly responsibility subsumes the
      previous roles. So, a developer requires all the same tools and resources as a user, similarly
      a committer requires all the tools and resources of a developer and so on. Each role may use
      the tools in a different way. It is therefore important to consider the different tool uses
      when selecting from the alternatives available.</p>

    <figure src="supportingCommunityRoles.png"
      alt="Community roles require various outputs from the project, and are supported by a few essential tools."
      width="100%"/>

    <section>
      <title>Supporting Users</title>

      <p>Anyone who contributes to a project must first become a user, that is they must first
        understand what the project can and can't do, they must be able to understand what is in
        scope and what is not. As such the education and support of the user is the first priority
        in any project wishing to reach sustainability. However, there is little point in supporting
        users unless they are first being attracted to the project.</p>

      <p>In order to attract users to the project it is vital that the project is able to
        disseminate information about itself in an efficient and meaningful way. A clear and
        understandable user section on the project website is clearly important here. However, it is
        also important to provide information for third party sites. One technique that is of
        considerable value is to provide data about the project in a machine readable form, such as a
          <a href="http://www.oss-watch.ac.uk/resources/doap.xml"
          title="Project Catalogues and Project Descriptors using DOAP">DOAP (Description of a
          Project)</a> file.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Supporting Developers</title>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Supporting Developers</title>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Supporting Communication</title>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Decision Making</title>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
