<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  
  Copyright 2007 University of Oxford
  
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  
  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
  
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Developing Simal Core</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>
      This document describes how to work with Simal Core in a
      development environment. Simal use Maven to manage its build
      process. So any IDE that supports Maven can be used, that includes
      the command line!
    </p>

    <section>
      <title>Prerequisites</title>

      <p>
        You must have set up the {{{download.html} prerequisites and
        downloaded}} the source for Simal Core.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Building with Maven</title>

      <p>
        To build Simal Core with Maven all you need to do is (from
        within your Simal Core home directory):
      </p>

      <source>mvn compile</source>

      <p>
        The first time you run this command Maven will automatically
        download all the dependencies needed for compilation. This means
        you must be connected to the Internet to run the command.
      </p>

      <p>
        In order to verify that your install has worked you can run the
        test suite with:
      </p>

      <source>mvn test</source>


      <p>
        Simal provides a command line interface (CLI) for working with
        core, other interfaces are possible, such as the separate web
        application found in the module uk.ac.osswatch.simal.web. It is
        outside the scope of this document to discuss these other
        interfaces. However, a very brief introduction to the CLI is
        useful at this point since it means you can can start playing
        immediately.
      </p>

      <p>
        To use the CLI you must first build a distribution with the
        following command.
      </p>

      <source>mvn assembly:assembly</source>

      <p>Now you can run the CLI with a command such as</p>

      <source>
        java -cp
        target/simal-core-0.1-SNAPSHOT-jar-with-dependencies.jar
        uk.ac.osswatch.simal.Simal -h
      </source>

      <note>
        You may need to change the version number ("0.1-SNAPSHOT" in the
        above example).
      </note>

      <p>
        The above command displays the CLI help message, try a few of
        the described commands out.
      </p>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Building Reports</title>

      <p>
        If you are working on the code of Simal Core then you will want
        to build the reports to check everything is OK, simply use:
      </p>

      <source>mvn site</source>

      <p>
        The site will be built in SIMAL_CORE/target/site. Point your
        browser at the index.html file in this folder and you will see
        the full range of documentation and reports available.
      </p>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Using Eclipse</title>

      <p>
        If you use Eclipse as your IDE then you can set up an Eclipse
        project with the command:
      </p>

      <source>mvn eclipse:eclipse</source>

      <p>
        We also recommend that you install the
        <a href="http://code.google.com/p/q4e/">Q4e</a>
        plugin and enable Maven Dependency Management to simplfy the
        management of your classpath within Eclipse.
      </p>

      <section>
        <title>Mylyn and Google Code</title>

        <p>
          Eclipse 3.3 and onwards includes the excellent Mylyn task
          management tool. You may want to configure Mylyn to work with
          our Issue Tracker, in which case you will find this
          <a
            href="http://www.jroller.com/alexRuiz/entry/using_mylyn_with_google_code">
            blog
          </a>
          from Alex Ruiz very useful (well I did anyway).
        </p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Installing Simal Core</title>

      <p>
        Simal Core is a library. There is no installation as such.
        However, for other Maven built applications to use this library
        it needs to be made available in your local Maven repository.
        Simply run:
      </p>

      <source>mvn install</source>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Now What?</title>

      <p>So you have Simal Core installed, now what?</p>
      
      <p>Simal core comes complete with a command line interface.
      This is intended to be self documenting, to run it add 
      the <code>bin</code>directory of Simal core to your
      <code>PATH</code> environment variable and run 
      <code>simal.bat --help</code> or 
      <code>simal.sh --help</code>.</p>

      <p>
        The Simal project provides a web application for working with
        Simal Core. You'll probably want to download that too.
      </p>

      <p>
        Alternatively, you may be interested in building your own
        application on top of the Simal Core library. If this is the
        case then, at this early stage, we encourage you to join our
        <a href="ext:simal/devList">mailing list</a>
        .
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>