<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2007 University of Oxford

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Sustainability Plan for Simal</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>Sustainability plans adapt over time. This document is intended to capture snapshots of
      Simal's sustainability plans as the project progresses.</p>

    <p>Simal is a framework for building systems for use by organisations that need to inform the
      communities around a group of related projects. It was initiated in March 2007 with the OSS
      Watch team based at Oxford University Computing Services.</p>



    <section id="march2007">
      <title>March 2007</title>
      <p>Having started Simal to meet a specific need within the OSS Watch project plan (see <a
          href="/projecthistory.html">Project History</a>), it makes sense that the initial
        sustainability plan for Simal involves a portion of OSS Watch's funded effort. The initial
        plan distinguishes between <em>short-term</em>, <em>mid-term</em>, and <em>long-term</em>
        sustainability, but does not specify dates for these divisions.</p>

      <section>
        <title>Short-term</title>
        <p>The project was always intended to build a voluntary development community around itself.
          However, a direct contribution of OSS Watch staff time is required to see Simal through
          from its initial inception to its presence on a publicly accessible hosted development
          environment. That contribution is estimated at 0.1 FTE (full time equivalent) over 4
          months.</p>
        <p>In addition, OSS Watch staff are contributing voluntary effort on evenings and weekends
          to the project.</p>
        <p>Since the funded committment to the project is finite, the first order of business is to
          develop a viable development community.</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Mid-term</title>
        <p>At some point in the not too distant future Simal will be a fully functioning project. At
          that point its outputs will undoubtedly be in use on the OSS Watch site, and hopefully
          some other sites. It may be possible at that point in time to apply for project-specific
          funding from JISC or some other funding body in order to sustain direct OSS Watch staff contribution to Simal.
          However, the project needs to anticipate that funding will not be forthcoming. It
          therefore needs to have a viable and growing voluntary development community in place. </p>

      </section>

      <section>

        <title>Long-term</title>

        <p>At this point it is difficult to guess where Simal might go under the influence of a
          consensus-based development community. Long term sustainability at this point sees that
          community continuing to develop Simal in order to meet its own needs. </p>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section id="exitstrategies">
      <title>Exit Strategies</title>

      <p>There are a number of possible exit strategies Simal. These might arise as real
        possibilities at different points within the project.</p>
      <ul>
        <li>the Simal community flourishes and continues to develop Simal along its present path</li>
        <li>the Simal community seeks to transform Simal into an Apache Incubator project or as part of some other software foundation</li>
        

      </ul>
      <p>These are by no means the only possible exit strategies for Simal. This list will be
        revised and expanded as new possibilities emerge over the course of the project.</p>
    </section>


  </body>
</document>
