<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  
  Copyright 2007 University of Oxford
  
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  
  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
  
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Data Management</title>
    <abstract>
      Simal uses an RDF repository to manage its data. This document
      describes how data is handled on ingest and how it can be
      accessed using the API.
    </abstract>
  </header>
  <body>
    <warning>This document describes intended functionality in the 0.3 release
    of Simal. Not all features described within it have been implemented.</warning>
    <section>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <p>Simal allows data about an entity can be collected 
      from multiple sources and then retrieved according to a
      hierarchy of preferred data sources. This allows an application
      to retrieve the most appropriate data available whilst still
      ensuring that all data known about an entity is available to it.</p>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Simal Entities</title>
      
      <p>When a project is imported into Simal a local instance of
      the entity is created. For example, suppose we import an entity
      with the URI <code>http://foo.org/originalSource</code> t6he
      following description will be created:</p>
      
      <source><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<RDF xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
  <Project rdf:about="http://simal.oss-watch.ac.uk/doap/26#Project"
           xmlns="http://usefulinc.com/ns/doap#"
           xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
           xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/"
           xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" 
           xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#">
     <rdf:sameAs rdf:resource="http://foo.org/originalSource"/>
   </Project>
</RDF>
      ]]></source>
      
      <p>Note the <code>rdf:sameAs</code> element, this indicates 
      an alternative source for information about this entity. At 
      this stage the internal Simal representation does not contain 
      any additional data and thus any requests for information about
      this entity will result in the data held in the original
      resource description being returned.</p>
      
      <p>The above annotation of the resource is handled by
      <code>uk.ac.osswatch.simal.model.Ingester</code>.</p>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Augmenting Third Party Data</title>
      <p>Whenever data about a resources is added us9ing any of the
      Simal tools rather than imported from an external resource,
      this data is recorded in the Simal data instance. For example,
      Adding a local description to an entity would result in the
      following being added to the local data tuples.</p>
      
      <source><![CDATA[
<description>A local description of this project.</p></description>
      ]]></source>
      
      <p>Under normal circumstances data held in the local instance
      description of the entity is given priority over other sources.
      However, this behaviour can be configured as described in the next
      section.</p>
    </section>     
    
    <section>
      <title>Selecting the Preferred Data Source</title>
      
      <p>When a second data source is imported Simal records the
      second source, using an <code>rdf:sameAs</code> element, in
      the internal Simal entity description.</p>
      
      <fixme author="RDG">Design a method for indicating priorities
      for data sources when retrieving data from multiple locations</fixme>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
