<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2007 University of Oxford

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE howto PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD How-to V2.0//EN"
"http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/howto-v20.dtd">
<howto>
  <header>
    <title>History of the Simal project</title>

    <version>0.01</version>

    <abstract>This document describes the steps taken to set up and maintain the Simal project.</abstract>

    <last-modified-content-date date="2007-03-04"/>
  </header>

  <audience title="Intended Audience">
    <p>Anyone interested in the history of the Simal project.</p>
  </audience>

  <purpose title="Purpose">
    <p>This document should not be misconstrued as the definitive history of the Simal project.
      Rather it attempts to take account of each significant decision-point as it came along. Our
      memories are faulty at best, and we hope this is a way to provide some guidance for other
      projects that might wish to go down a similar path; guidance both for what to do, and for what
      not to do.</p>
  </purpose>

  <steps title="Steps">
    <p>How the Simal project developed</p>

    <section id="initiation">
      <title>Initial discussion of possible project for OSS Watch</title>

      <p>Although members of the OSS Watch team had bandied the idea of setting up an open source
        development project themselves for some time, discussion in earnest did not begin until the
        addition of Ross Gardler to the team in January 2007. Ross' experience as a member of The
        Apache Software Foundation, his concerted focus on the need to develop a community around
        any open development project, and his practical suggestion of a framework for building a DOAP
        catalogue solidified our wishful thinking into something more like the seed of a project.</p>

      <p>However, even with the seed of a project in place, we faced a set of immediate decisions:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>should this project be set within Oxford University Computing Services (where the OSS
          Watch team is located)</li>
        <li>should we use an established open source project hosting site, such as SourceForge or
          Google Code</li>
        <li>would this project be intended to serve more than just the end of producing a particular
          software application <ul>
            <li>the project could be a means of developing reusable documentation for other open
              development projects</li>
            <li>the project could be a means of establishing a new practice of open development at
              Oxford University Computing Services</li>
            <li>the project could be a means for OSS Watch staff to <em>learn by doing</em> through
              participation in an open development project</li>
          </ul></li>
        <li>what licence should we choose for our code and our documentation</li>
        <li>how would we get other user/developers involved</li>
        <li>what steps could we take now to make the project sustainable in the long run</li>
      </ul>
      <p>There were other considerations as well but the above probably constitute the most
        significant points. With so many decision points the project could easily have turned into a
        talking point rather than an actual open development project. Fortunately that did not turn
        out to be the case.</p>
    </section>

    <section id="first-codebase">
      <title>First Codebase</title>

      <p>On Friday, 2 March 2007, Ross Gardler sent an email to the other members of the OSS Watch
        team entitled: <em>Simal is born (DOAP catalogue)</em>. In that email, Ross outlined the
        initial thrust of the project, where the codebase for the project was located, and how we
        could each begin contributing.</p>

      <source>
        <![CDATA[
      I just committed Simal to our new projects svn space.
      
      Simal is the current working title for the DOAP catalogue. If you want to suggest a real name please 
      go ahead - however names should not reflect what the project does, things tend to go in unexpected 
      directions in open source.
      
      Current Status
      ==============
      
      The catalogue is currently in an early prototype stage. To view the current 
      catalogue functionality follow the links in the catalogue menu on the left of 
      the above linked page. For more information about the current status and 
      recent changes in the catalogue code see the recent changes  document 
      (you can subscribe to a changes RSS feed if you prefer - note this is a 
      temporary location for the feed).
      
      What Needs to be Done
      =====================
      
      In order to move forward with the development of the catalogue we need 
      to increase the number of projects represented with DOAP files, and we 
      need to extend the information stored in current projects files. The files 
      are stored at \src\documentation\content\rdf feel free to edit them (until 
      the project finds a permanent home I'm happy for everyone to have commit 
      access to the code base).
      
      Since Ramon showed some interest, it would also be really cool if we could 
      have a package for Simal and for Forrest to make the getting start part even 
      easier. I have no idea how to do this but there are plenty of people in the 
      building who can help. It would be great if Ramon could also donate the 
      config for doing the Forrest part back to the Forrest community.
      
      Getting Started
      ===============
      
      Try this document for size [with a link to the Quick Start doc on the seed 
      project site]
      ]]>
      </source>

      <p>The initial codebase was deposited in an OSS Watch projects subversion repository. That was
        always meant to be a temporary holding point until we made some early decisions.</p>

      <p>With a subversion repository accessible to the OSS Watch team, the project could be said to
        have officially started.</p>


    </section>

    <section id="initial-discussion">
      <title>Initial discussion</title>

      <p>Throughout those first few days the team engaged in wide-spread discussion about a number
        of issues. More than 50 emails were exchanged on the team email list.</p>

      <ul>
        <li>which licence should the project adopt?</li>
        <li>the project name - what does Simal mean?; nothing, it's just a name</li>
        <li>what is a meritocracy?</li>
        <li>what do we do if we want to contribute a patch to the Apache Forrest project? 
          <ul>
            <li>the initial project site and codebase for Simal drew heavily on the achievements of
              the Apache Forrest project. It was perfectly natural therefore that participants in
              Simal might also find opportunities to contribute to the Apache Forrest project. In
              order for that to take place, however, since the team members were all employees of
              the University of Oxford, an Apache Coporate Contributor License Agreement would need
              to be signed on our behalf by someone with the authority to do so, in this case the
              Director of Oxford University Computing Services.</li>
            
          </ul>
        </li>
        <li>have we set up the initial subversion repository correctly?</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Lots to think about and lots to decide.</p>
    </section>
    
    <section id="firstContributions">
      <title>First Contributions</title>
      
      <p>Within days of being started the Simal project recieved important contributions
      from other OSS Watch members. Many of these contributions were not
      technical in nature, but are good examples of the non-technical contributions
      new users of a project can make quickly and easily. These contributions included:</p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>Testing and bug reporting</li>
        <li>Documentation corrections</li>
        <li>New documentation (this document for example)</li>
        <li>Expansion of DOAP data available to the system</li>
        <li>Contribution of an external DOAP file from a third party project, in this case WebPA at Loughborough University</li>
      </ul>
      
      <p>These contributions show the value of the release early, release often
      approach commonly found in open source software development. Early releases
      enable early feedback and contributions from interested parties. As long
      as user expectations are managed correctly, for example known bugs are
      clearly identified in the release documentation, exposing your early work,
      "warts and all" is the start to building an early community.</p>
    </section>
    <section id="earlydescisions">
      <title>Early decisions</title>
      <p>Before one month had passed the team discussion had reached consensus on two important points:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>licence: Apache License, version 2.0
        <ul>
          <li>After intensively exploring a number of options the consensus was that Simal should be released 
            under the <a href="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0.html">Apache License, version 2.0</a>.
            This licence was chosen as we believe that it provides the most flexibility
            for likely downstream projects wishing to utilise the Simal outputs. In addition it also address a possible 
          long term plan for the <a href="sustainabilityplan.html">sustainability</a> of the project</li>
        
          
        </ul>
          
        </li>
        <li>project home: Google Code
        <ul>
          <li>Hosting the project on Google Code serves a number of ends. Google Code has many of the advantages 
          of SourceForge without the association with more than 100,000 moribund projects. It has Google behind it, which 
          bodes well for the ongoing development of its facilities. No one in the team had used it before (other than to 
          explore its feature set), so it would provide a learning opportunity for everyone. Plus we thought it would be fun.</li>
        </ul>
        </li>
      </ul>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="approval">
      <title>Agreement of plans from copyright holders and funding bodies</title>
      
      <p>OSS Watch, who are the first intended users of the Simal system, are
      a part of Research Technologies Service at Oxford University Computing
      Services (OUCS). Since OSS Watch time will be donated to this project 
      it was necessary to get approval from OSS Watch's Director at OUCS before making this project
      public.</p>
      
      <p>To this end Ross Gardler and Randy Metcalfe of OSS Watch created a
      project description brief that looked at the immediate benefits to OSS Watch, JISC (the Joint 
      Information Systems Committee) - OSS Watch's funder, and OUCS.
      This was submitted to Mike Fraser, Director of OSS Watch who approved the
      allocation of 0.1 FTE to the project over 4 months. Not much, but enough
      to get things going.</p>
      
      <p>Next stage is to take this project description to Ann Borda, OSS Watch's 
        JISC Programme Manager. </p>
    </section>
      
  </steps>

  <!--
  <extension title="Extension">
    <p>Solutions can be extended to cover many different problem domains. A nearly unlimited number
      of potential How-To topics, from simple to complex, are available right now, limited only by
      your imagination.</p>
  </extension>

  <faqs id="faqs">
    <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
    <faqsection id="faq-general">
      <title>General issues</title>
      <faq id="faq-difference">
        <question>What is the difference between a How-To and a tutorial?</question>

        <answer>
          <p>The goal of a How-To is to help the reader to accomplish a specific task with clear and
            consise instructions. While tutorials may contain How-To-like instructions and content,
            they also include additional background and conceptual content to help teach their
            readers higher order concepts along the way. How-Tos are concerned about filling an
            immediate, short-term need. Tutorials often provide long-term knowledge which can be
            applied across a range of needs.</p>
        </answer>
      </faq>
    </faqsection>

    <faqsection id="faq-style">
      <title>Style issues</title>
      <faq id="spelling">
        <question>What spelling convention should I follow?</question>

        <answer>
          <p>Use whatever spelling convention (American, British, etc.) that is most intuitive to
            you.</p>
        </answer>
      </faq>
    </faqsection>
  </faqs>

  <tips title="Tips">
    <section id="tip-dtd">
      <title>How-To dtd</title>

      <p>The document structure is likely to change at some time. Please note that this HOWTO page
        is likely to change as well.</p>
    </section>
  </tips>

  <references title="References">
    <p>This is not the first, nor will it be the last, How-To on writing How-Tos. For other ideas
      and opinions on the matter, check out the following sources.</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Joel D. Canfield's <a
          href="http://www.evolt.org/article/How_To_Write_A_How_To/9741/18250/index.html">How to
          Write a How-To</a> on evolt.org.</li>

      <li>The Linux Documentation Project's <a
          href="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/HOWTO-INDEX/index.html">HOWTO</a> index page provides many
        excellent How-To documents to inspire your efforts.</li>
    </ul>
  </references>
  -->
</howto>
