<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2007 University of Oxford
  
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  
  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Documentation Structure</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <p>There are three sites in the Simal project:</p>

    <ul>
      <li>
        <a href="ext:simal/projectSite">Project site</a>
        - jumping off point for everyone
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="ext:simal/devSite">
          Developer site - all the project management and development
          tools
        </a>
      </li>
      <li>
        <a href="ext:simal/demoSite">
          Demo site - a demo site running a development version of Simal
        </a>
      </li>
    </ul>


    <p>
      There is also a small amount of dev focussed content on the
      <a href="ext:simal/wiki">wiki</a>
      . This content is either documentation for in-development
      features, i.e. not to be published on the main Simal project site,
      or it is content that relates to the management of the Simal
      project but is not (in most cases) relevant to the project site.
    </p>

    <section>
      <title>Project Site</title>

      <p>
        The
        <a href="ext:simal/projectSite">project site</a>
        is the main information site for the Simal project. On this site
        you will find:
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li>User documentation</li>
        <li>Developer documentation</li>
        <li>Project management documentation</li>
      </ul>

      <p>
        The project site is generated using
        <a href="http://forrest.apache.org">Apache Forrest</a>
        . It consists of a master site and a number of subsites, one for
        each of the modules found in the Simal project. The source for
        the master site can be found in
        <code>simal/src/documentation/content/xdocs</code>
        in our
        <a href="ext:simal/svn">SVN</a>
        . Sources for each of the sub sites are found in the respective
        svn modules, for example, the core module site sources are in
        <code>
          uk.ac.osswatch.simal.core/src/documentation/content/xdocs
        </code>
        .
      </p>

      <note>
        A small number of pages in the project site are generated from
        source in the developer site wiki. This is to prevent the need
        to duplicate content accross the two sites. If you can't find
        the source for a file in the above locations then it will almost
        certainly be in the wiki. See the next section.
      </note>

      <p>
        You can build either the main site documentation of any of the
        individual subsites by running the following command in the root
        directory of the relevant module (after installing Apache
        Forrest):
      </p>

      <source>forrest site</source>

      <p>
        This will build a static version of the site in the
        <code>build/site</code>
        directory.
      </p>

      <p>
        When writing new content it is best to run a version of Forrest
        in dynamic mode. This allows you to edit files and see the
        changes immediately. To run Forrest in dynamic mode simply execute
        the command
        <code>forrest run</code>
        , and then point your browser at
        <code>http://localhost:8888</code>
        .
      </p>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Developer Site</title>

      <p>
        The
        <a href="ext:simal/devSite">developer site</a>
        is where you will find all the tools for project management and
        development, such as:
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li>Mailing lists</li>
        <li>Issue tracker</li>
        <li>svn</li>
        <li>Wiki</li>
      </ul>

      <section>
        <title>Wiki</title>

        <p>The developer site wiki contains two types of data:</p>

        <ul>
          <li>Documentation for in development features</li>
          <li>
            Project management documentation that is not applicable to
            the main site
          </li>
        </ul>

        <p>
          The first type of content, documentation for in development
          features, is content that is evolving quickly and should not
          be placed on the main site. Often this documentation will be
          incomplete or of a discussive nature.
        </p>

        <p>
          The second type of content, project management materials, is
          content that is not of general interest to Simal users and
          contributors. That is, it is content only of interest to the
          project maintainers. It is kept on the wiki in order to
          prevent it polluting searches of the project site.
        </p>

        <p>
          It is possible to include content from the wiki in the project
          site. This will occasionally be necessary to prevent
          duplication of content. Generally this practice should be
          avoided.
        </p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Demo Site</title>
      
      <p>The <a href="ext:simal/demoSite">demo site</a> runs a recent version
      of Simal for demonstration purposes. It is regularly updated and the 
      repository is flushed and re-seeded with sample data.</p>
      
      <warning>As the demo site is used to show new features it will often be
      the first place that bugs appear. As Simal stabilises we will set up 
      a stable demo, but for now the demo site is assumed to be for test
      purposes only.</warning>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
