<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2007 University of Oxford

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>Simal - A Project Support Framework</title> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
  
    <p>Simal is a tool for building and tracking projects and the people involved in
      those projects. Simal is very young at this time. As
      such, <a href="http://code.google.com/p/simal">we welcome input</a>
      into the requirements and design of the initial prototype system.</p>
    
    <section>
      <title>Quick Start</title>
      
      <p>This site provides a small project catalogue as an example of Simal can do.
      The catalogue is generated from RDF documents maintained and hosted by
      the projects themselves or, where no such document exists, by the Simal project.
      View the catalogue by clicking on the catalogue link above, or by using our
      <a href="catalogueBrowser.html">AJAX powered browser</a>.</p>
      
      <p>Want to get at the code? The impatient may like our 
      <a href="quickstart.html">quick start</a> documentation.</p>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      
      <p>Simal is an open source framework for building systems for use by those
    who need to inform a community about the activities of multiple projects
    that may be hosted in multiple locations. Each project maintains an entry 
    within the Simal project catalogue by means of an RDF/XML file. This entry 
    contains a description of what the project is doing, team members, community 
    structure, deliverables, etc. Simal uses this file to gather a range of 
    information about the projects and presents it in various forms to suit 
    a variety of uses, such as a web site, or PDF document.</p>
      
      <p>Simal also provides a web application for the creation and management
      of catalogues built using this system. This application allows users to
      identity projects of interest to their community and generate customised 
      catalogues for their own use, within their own projects website.</p>
            
      <p>The generated catalogues present a useful community 
      development and support tool. They enable users to 
      quickly and easily track activity in multiple related projects from 
      a single location. Thus a projects outputs are visible beyond its
      immediate community. By exposing relevant outputs to a wider community
      we hope to increase the level of interaction between related projects.</p>
      
      <p>The project is very young at this time. As
      such, we welcome input into the requirements and design of the
      initial prototype system.</p>
  </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Overview</title>
      
      <section>
        <title>Project Catalogue</title>
        <p>The project catalogue is built by importing Description of a Project (DOAP)
          files from projects. Once made available to the system these DOAP files
          are aggregated and presented in various ways that allow a catalogue of
          projects to be presented and manipulated. This catalogue can be used to
          find relationships (either existing or potential) between projects.</p>
        
        <section>
          <title>Status</title>
          <p>The catalogue is currently in an early prototype stage. To view the
            current catalogue functionality follow the links in the catalogue menu
            on the left. For more information about the current status and recent
            changes in the catalogue code see the <a href="/changes.html">recent changes</a>
            document (you can subscribe to a <a href="changes.rss">changes RSS feed</a> if you prefer).</p>
          
          <p>In order to move forward with the development of the catalogue we
            need to increase the number of projects represented with DOAP files, and
            we need to extend the information stored in current projects files.</p>
        </section>
      </section>
      
      <section>
        <title>Community Support</title>
        <p>The community support systems allow individuals or groups to manage
          public and private information concerning the communties that develop around
          open source projects. The application allows project managers and developers
          to effortlessly inform their communities about changes in the project
          make-up and community tools. There is also a set of tools for identifying
          potential collaboration points between communities.</p>
        
        <section>
          <title>Status</title>
          
          <p>The community support features are still in an early stage of
            planning. We welcome contributions to the initial requirements 
            gathering processes.</p>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Contributing</title>
      
      <p>Simal is an open source project that adopts an open development
        methodology. We welcome contributions from anyone, such contributions
        may include (but are not limited to):</p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>User feedback such as bug reports and feature requests</li>
        <li>User support such as documentation and mailing list participation</li>
        <li>Graphic and web design</li>
        <li>Community development</li>
        <li>Design</li>
        <li>Patches addressing bugs or adding new features</li>
      </ul>
      
      <p>Use the Contributor tab above to be taken to the <a href="contributor/index.html">contributor
        section</a> where you will find more information on how to help Simal
        improve.</p>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Why Simal?</title>
      <p>What does the name <a href="whySimal.html">Simal</a> mean?</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
