<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2007 University of Oxford

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>Simal - A Project Registry Framework</title> 
  </header> 
  <body> 
  
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>
	    <p>Simal is an open source tool for building project registries. 
	     Simal uses the Description of a Project (DOAP) schema to collect, store and present 
	     data about projects. Simal is available under the 
       <a href="http://www.oss-watch.ac.uk/resources/apache2.xml">Apache software License V2</a>.</p>
	      
	    <p id="missionStatement">The mission of the Simal project is to create 
	    a software framework for the collection and management of essential details
	    about open development projects. Using this data it will be possible
	    to create a picture of development projects and communities, that allows
	    for all increased awareness of existing projects and experts to be found 
	    within.</p>
	    
	    <warning>Simal is very young at this time, it works, but is far from feature
	    complete. As such, we welcome input into the requirements and design of the 
	    initial system via our <a href="ext:simal/devList">mailing list</a>.</warning>
	</section>

	
    <section>
      <title>Quick Links</title>
	    <ul>
	      <li><a href="quickstart.html">Quick Start</a> - for the impatient who want to go straight to the code</li>
	      
	      <li><a href="overview.html">Overview</a> - for those who want the 20,000 foot view</li>
	    
	      <li><a href="ext:simal/demoSite">Demo server</a> - for those who want to take a look</li>
	    </ul>
	</section>
	
    <section>
      <title>Contributing</title>
      
      <p>Simal is an open source project that adopts an open development
        methodology. We welcome contributions from anyone, such contributions
        may include (but are not limited to):</p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>User feedback such as bug reports and feature requests</li>
        <li>User support such as documentation and mailing list participation</li>
        <li>Graphic and web design</li>
        <li>Community development</li>
        <li>Design</li>
        <li>Patches addressing bugs or adding new features</li>
      </ul>
      
      <p>Use the Contributor tab above to be taken to the <a href="contributor/index.html">contributor
        section</a> where you will find more information on how to help Simal
        improve.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
