<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2007 University of Oxford

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>What is Simal?</title>
  </header> 
  <body>       
    <section>
      <title>Introduction to Simal</title>
      
      <p>Simal aims to be a community development 
      and support tool. It will facilitate relationships between projects and contributors to 
      those projects. It will enable users to quickly identify 
      groups of projects and individuals with whom they share a common goal.
      </p>
      
      <p>In its simplest form, Simal will be a project catalogue. It will enable
      users of the catalogue to search and filter data 
      along a great many data axis. As the tool matures both manual and
      semi-automated features for
      discovering projects and people in specific areas of interest will be
      added. In order to do this it will build upon growing interest in
      the semantic web and web 2.0 technologies.</p>
      
      <p>Simal will be an open source project, hosted on Google Code. It is
      expected to be released under the <a href="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0.html">Apache License Version 2.0</a>.
      This licence was chosen as we believe that it provides the most flexibility
      for downstream projects wishing to utilise the Simal outputs.</p>
    
        <section>
          <title>Governance Model</title>
          
          <p>Simal's governance model will be community-based consensus, similar to that
          found within The Apache Software Foundation projects. Decisions about 
          the future of the project will be made through discussion
          with all members of the community, from the newest user to the most
          experienced contributor. When consensus cannot be easily gained through discussion a
          voting procedure will be used. Binding votes are awarded to
          those who demonstrate an understanding of the project's objectives
          and governance model through a positive involvement with the project community.</p>
        </section>
      
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Why is OSS Watch leading Simal?</title>
      
      <p>OSS Watch is a JISC-funded development service which promotes 
      awareness and understanding of the legal, social, 
      technical and economic issues that arise when educational institutions 
      engage with free and open source software. Within this remit
      OSS Watch provides guidance to projects wishing
      to create open source projects. It is useful for
      OSS Watch to illustrate key aspects of consensus-based open source software development 
      in practice. Simal will serve both as opportunity for OSS Watch to explore the practicialities of 
      this form of open source development, while at the same time providing an exemplar for JISC 
      projects with respect to typical governance models, community building, release management,
      quality assurance, user support and documentation. It will involve a commitment of approximately 
      0.1  FTE of effort over 4 months to reach public launch.</p>
      
      <p>However, Simal is no mere project <em>template</em>. OSS Watch fully intend to deploy the outputs 
        from Simal, i.e. a project catalogue, in order to serve as a means of building community relationships <em>between</em> 
        JISC development projects. This is a task OSS Watch had set itself previously and Simal will help fulfil it. Simal itself, of course, draws upon significant work done by other open source projects, e.g. 
        Apache Forrest, Apache Wicket, Databinder and Hibernate, and its own entry in the catalogue will reflect this.</p>

      <p>To summarize, the benefits to OSS Watch in leading Simal are:</p>
        
        <ul>
          <li>ongoing practical engagement for OSS Watch team members in a consensus-based open source development project</li>
          <li>learning points reflected back to JISC projects as advice and guidance</li>
          <li>project catalogue of JISC development projects to be deployed on OSS Watch website</li>
        </ul>
                      
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>What benefit will Simal provide to the JISC?</title>
      
      <p>The most immediate and obvious benefit to JISC Development is the provision
      of a project template that other JISC-funded projects may freely adopt and adapt
      as their individual needs demand. OSS Watch already provides
      consultation support to projects. The Simal documentation set will allow this
      consultation to be more guided and more effective. These templates
      will, we hope, be living documents that will over time grow to reflect the 
      diverse needs of JISC projects.</p>
      
      <p>A further practical benefit to JISC projects will be the opportunity to use the Simal catalogue 
        tool for their own needs.
      For example, JISC CETIS
      maintains an e-learning project catalogue. The adoption of
      Simal will remove the need to duplicate efforts between OSS Watch and
      JISC CETIS. Similarly, individual projects will be able to publish
      more focused catalogues relating to their local communities without
      needing to expend considerable energy in maintaining those catalogues.
      </p>
      
      <p>Simal can also be used to increase the wider awareness of JISC-funded projects without 
        additional overhead on individual
      projects. This is achieved through a mechanism that allows projects
      to submit their publicly available data to third party catalogues
      with very little additional effort. Individual projects maintain a single
        machine readable file for all catalogue entries, a <a href="http://www.oss-watch.ac.uk/resources/doap.xml">DOAP file</a>. 
        This file is stored on 
      the project's own web server and conforms to a standard format reconised
      by other catalogue systems such as O'Reilly's CodeZoo. Modifications to
      all catalogues featuring the project can be made by editing this single
      locally managed file. This reduction in overhead in maintaining catalogue entries
      results in more accurate and more widespread data about JISC-funded projects.</p>
      
      <p>The JISC could benefit from this increased data accuracy and availability
      directly. For example, the JISC could use this data to create
      the "What We Do" section of the JISC website. In the future, the Simal
      system could be used to provide data for the proposed PIMS application, thus
      minimising the effort required by programme managers in ensuring the
      PIM data is accurate.</p>
      
      <p>Finally, Simal is able to 
      collate and link to data in existing JISC databases.
      For example, it can utilise and relate to information provided in the
      e-framework database and the standards catalogue. As such Simal could
      be used to draw valuable data from disparate projects within the JISC
      and present it in a uniform, accurate and, where approprite, secure 
      way.</p>
      
      <p>To summarize, the benefits to JISC from the Simal project are:</p>
      
      <ul>
        <li>consensus-based project templates as an adaptable model for other JISC projects</li>
        <li>JISC projects able to maintain their own Simal catalogues</li>
        <li>projects able to spread news of their project through project-maintained DOAP file</li>
        <li>possible use of project catalogue on JISC website</li>
        </ul>
        
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>What benefit will Simal bring to the OUCS?</title>
      
      <p>Simal will be clearly identified on Google Code as an OSS Watch project. OSS Watch 
        is consistently identified as a JISC-funded project hosted by Oxford University Computing Services. 
        OUCS will thus gain recognition through this effort.</p>
      
      <p>OUCS could also use the Simal output to collate information about OUCS projects whether internal or 
        externally funded. Internal project teams can use it to discover
      related projects, individuals and communities both inside and outside 
      of OUCS. In general, Simal will facilitate a more informed management of internal 
      projects.</p>
      
      <p>The framework will be designed to be extensible so, for example, it
      could be extended to formally support the data
      required in OUCS' internal "light touch" project management methodology. By
      customising Simal in this way, OUCS will be able to collate this valuable
      information in a more useful human and machine readable form. This paves the
      way for more effective reuse of the knowledge acquired within OUCS projects.</p>    
      
      <p>To summarize, the benefits to OUCS from the Simal project are:</p>
      <ul>
        <li>associated branding on a Google Code project</li>
        <li>possible use to collate information about OUCS projects</li>
        <li>possible extension of Simal to accommodate data from OUCS "light touch" project management methodology</li>
      </ul>
      
      
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
