<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2007 Oxford University

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Simal - Quick Start</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <warning>This is very early days and very experimental. There are things that don't work, broken
      links in generated content etc.</warning>

    <note>Since there is nothing in this code base that we hold dear (yet). we welcome constructive
      criticism about any aspect of the project, its outputs, its direction, its intentions or
      anything you feel is relevant.</note>

    <section>
      <title>Getting the Source</title>

      <p>The source can be checked out from SVN with:</p>

      <source>svn co https://svn.oucs.ox.ac.uk/projects/oss-watch/simal simal</source>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Building from Source</title>

      <p>There are two parts to Simal, an <a href="http://forrest.apache.org">Apache Forrest</a>
        generated Catalogue site and an <a href="http://incubator.apache.org/wicket">Apache
        Wicket</a> web application. For now the web application can be ignored by the average user
        since it does not do anything particularly useful. If you want to work on it then join our
        mailing lists.</p>

      <p>To work with the catalogue you will need to checkout an build Apache Forrest 0.8-dev (that
        is Forrest's current SVN head). The Forrest project has some excellent <a
          href="http://forrest.apache.org/docs_0_80/build.html">documentation</a> for this (it's
        easy, honest).</p>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Running the Catalogue Application</title>

      <p>Once you have Forrest installed change to your Simal directory and run the command
          <code>forrest run</code>. Now point your browser at <a href="http://localhost:8089"
          >http:localhost:8089</a> - that's it.</p>

      <note>We use a different port to the default Forrest port.</note>

      <p>You are now running the catalogue in dynamic mode. You can edit content files (stored in
        src/documentation/content/xdcos) and then refresh your browser to see the changes
        immediately. It's worth noting that this version of the catalogue also includes all the
        project documentation. So you can help us improve the documentation by running the catalogue
        and editing the files whilst you experiment. Use the Contributor tab above to be taken to
        the <a href="contributor/index.html">contributor section</a> where you will find more
        information on how to help Simal improve.</p>

      <section>
        <title>Static Content Generation</title>

        <p>It is possible to generate the catalogue as a static snapshot suitable for hosting on a
          normal web server or distributing via CD or other such means. To do this simply run the
          command <code>forrest site</code>.</p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Current Status</title>

      <p>To view the current catalogue functionality follow the links in the catalogue menu on the
        left of the above linked page. For more information about the current status and recent
        changes in the catalogue code see the recent changes document.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>What Needs to be Done</title>

      <p>In the contributor section of the catalogue site (see the "Contributor" tab above) you will
        find a "To Do" menu item this will give an indication of some of the tasks that we need to
        tackle. However, if you want to contribute in some other way, please feel free to make
        proposals on our mailing list.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Getting Help/Providing Feedback</title>

      <p>We do not have a permanent home for this project yet. So the OSS Watch list is our mailing
        list for now. We are still deciding where it should live permanently - suggestions welcome.</p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Open Source?</title>
      <p>Whilst this will be an open source project it is not one at this time because we have not
        addressed the IPR and licensing issues, nor have we started to think about what licence is most
        appropriate.</p>

      <p>Therefore, if you do contribute to the project in any way it is assumed that you do so
        under your contract with Oxford University and therefore Oxford University owns the copyright
        to those contributions. If you are not an employee of Oxford university then I am afraid we
        are unable to accept your contributions at this time. We will resolve this very soon before
        the project goes public.</p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
