<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2007 Oxford University

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<useCases>
  <title>Use Cases for DOAP File Management</title>

  <useCase status="In Progress" owner="RDG">
    <title>Create a Standard DOAP File for Maintenance by the Project</title>
    <description>
      <p>A project developer visits the application, selects the option to create a
      new DOAP and is presented with a form containing fields for project details. They enter
      these details in the form and are presented with a complete DOAP file that can be
      stored in the projects document set.</p>

      <section>
        <title>Justification</title>

        <p>A DOAP file is allows a project to register their project with a number
        of external applications quickly and easily. Creating an initial DOAP file 
        requires some knowledge of the DOAP format. By providing a form to create
        a standard DOAP file we make it unnecessary for users to learn the schema,
        subsequent edits can be done using a standard text editor.</p>

      </section>      
    </description>

    <steps>
      <step>
        <title>Select "Create DOAP"</title>
        <description>
            The user selects an option to create a DOAP file in the user interface.
        </description>

        <result>A form is presented for creating a standard DOAP file.</result>

        <fixme priority="Low">Remove the copyright footer referring to OSS Watch</fixme>
        <fixme priority="Low">Remove references to OSS Watch in the html source file</fixme>
        <fixme priority="Low">Improve layout of the form</fixme>
        <fixme priority="Low">Write help documentation to work within the application.</fixme>
        
        <implementation>
          <description>
              <p>The source of the form can be found in <code>xdocs/doap/create.html</code> and
              is accessed via the URL http://localhost:8080/doap/create.html.</p>
          </description>
        </implementation>
      </step>

      <step>
        <title>Complete the form</title>

        <description>
          <p>The user completes the form with relevant values from their project.
          The application provides context specific help for each field.</p>
        </description>

        <result>The user has a completed and valid form.</result>

        <fixme priority="High">Create Javascript code to validate the form
        as valiues are entered.</fixme>

      </step>
      
      <step>
          <title>Build the DOAP file</title>
          <description>
            <p>The user clicks on the "Create" button and has a DOAP file returned to them,
            together with instructions on what to do with it now.</p>
          </description>
          
        <fixme priority="Blocker">Create Javascript code to build the DOAP file 
        and return it to the user</fixme>
        <fixme priority="Medium">Document what the user should now do with the DOAP file</fixme>
      </step>
    </steps>
  </useCase>
</useCases>
