<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2007 University of Oxford

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE faqs PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD FAQ V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/faq-v20.dtd">
<faqs>
  <title>Frequently Asked Questions (Users)</title>
  <faqsection id="CLI">
    <title>Working with people</title>
    <faq id="findingPeople">
      <question>
        How can I find people I may be interested in?
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>Perhaps the easiest way to find people is to use the
        people browser.</p>
        
        <p>To illustrate this let us assume we want to discover
        people who are engaged with "access management" 
        projects. To do this using the people browser we need 
        to:</p> 
        
        <p class="instruction">Click on "People Browser" in the
        main menu. We are initially presented with all the
        people in the registry.</p>

        <p class="instruction">Click "Access Management" in 
        the category facet selector (on the right).</p>

        <p>The results displayed now include only those 
        people who work on projects related to
        access management. Note that the project facet 
        browser has also been filtered to only those projects 
        that are active in the access management field.</p>
      </answer>
    </faq>
    
    <faq id="exportData">
      <question>
        How do I export data for use in my own application?
      </question>
      <answer>
        <p>There are two main ways of exporting data from
        Simal. One is to use the 
        <a href="http://simal.oss-watch.ac.uk/rest">REST API</a> ,
        the other is to use one of the web based browsers to 
        filter the information to the set of data you want and then
        export it using one of the export tools.</p>
        
        <p>To do this click the orange scissors icon in the
        browsers once you have filtered the data accordingly.
        You will be presented with a number of export formats,
        select one and you will be presented with the data you
        require. Simply copy and paste it into your 
        chosen application.</p> 
      </answer>
    </faq>
<!-- More faqs or parts here -->
  </faqsection>
</faqs>