<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2007 University of Oxford
  
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  
  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>New Committer Guidlines</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <p>
        If you are a new committer on Simal then this document should
        help you get started.
      </p>

      <p>
        First of all congratulations on being voted in as a committer.
        Having commit rights does not give you any more authority in the
        project, however it does indicate that you understand the
        direction the project is heading in and that you have
        demonstrated an ability to support the community. You are now
        able to provide contributions on a commit-then-review basis and,
        perhaps more importantly, you are able to review-then-commit
        other community members contributions.
      </p>

      <p>
        You also have a binding vote in the project. This should not be
        used to give you power in the community, it is intended to be
        used to ensure all votes properly reflect the wishes of the
        community as a whole. As such you are expected to listen to
        community members and vote in their best wishes.
      </p>

      <p>
        The rest of this document describes a few small tasks you need
        to undertake as a new committer.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Familiarisation</title>

      <p>
        You are probably already familiar with our project's
        <a href="index.html">governance model</a>
        , however, we recommend that you review it again. It is this
        governance model that ensures each member of our community is
        adequately represented and that the project is managed in an
        open and transparent way.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Documentation</title>

      <p>
        There are a few files you should edit as soon as your commit
        privileges have been granted.
      </p>

      <p>
        You should add yourself to the Simal DOAP file located at
        <code>simal/src/documentation/content/rdf/simal.xml</code>
        .
      </p>

      <p>
        You should also note your addition to the team in the status
        file (located at
        <code>simal/status.xml</code>)
        , ensuring you add yourself as a new developer if you are not
        already there.
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>