<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2007 University of Oxford
  
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at
  
  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
  
  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>Simal - User Quickstart</title>
  </header>
  <body>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>
        Simal is an open source tool for building project registries.
        Simal uses the Description of a Project (DOAP) schema to
        collect, store and present data about projects. Simal is
        available under the
        <a href="http://www.oss-watch.ac.uk/resources/apache2.xml">
          Apache software License V2
        </a>
        .
      </p>

      <p>
        This document describes how to download and install Simal on
        your local machine. We are concerned here with the latest binary
        release of Simal, if you want to work with the latest
        development release you'll need the developers
        <a href="devQuickstart.html">quickstart</a>
        . If you just want to see what Simal can do then you probably
        want to view our
        <a href="http://data.oss-watch.ac.uk:8080">demo server</a>
        .
      </p>

      <warning>
        Simal is very young at this time, it works, but is far from
        feature complete. As such, we welcome input into the
        requirements and design of the initial system via our
        <a href="ext:simal/devList">mailing list</a>
        .
      </warning>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Pre-Requisites</title>

      <p>
        In order to run Simal from the command line all you need is
        <a href="http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads/previous.jsp">
          Java JRE
        </a>
        1.5 +
      </p>

      <p>
        If you want to run the REST API or the Web application you will
        also need a servlet engine such as Jetty or Apache Tomcat.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Downloading</title>

      <p>
        All our releases are available on our
        <a href="ext:simal/downloadPage">developer site</a>
        . Visit that page and download the module you want to use, each
        module is described below:
      </p>

      <note>
        You only need to download a single module as all dependencies
        are included in each module.
      </note>

      <ul>
        <li>
          simal-web provides a web interface to the Simal repository.
          This is ideal if you wish to provide a human interface to the
          repository.
        </li>
        <li>
          simal-rest provides a REST interface to the Simal repository.
          This is ideal if you wish to write your own front end to a
          Simal repository.
        </li>
        <li>
          simal-core contains the minimum you need to work with Simal,
          that is the repository and command line interface for
          interacting with that repository. This module is ideal if you
          wish to write scripts and other low level applications for
          working with the repository.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Running</title>

      <p>
        How you run Simal depends on which module you have downloaded.
      </p>

      <section>
        <title>Simal Web</title>

        <p>
          To run the web application simply drop the
          <code>simal-webapp-VERSION.war</code>
          into your chosen servlet container and point your browser at
          http://localhost:PORT/simal-webapp-VERSION
        </p>

        <p>
          It should be notes that the web application bundles Simal REST
          with it. The endpoint for RESTful requests is
          http://localhost:PORT/simal-webapp-VERSION/simal-rest
        </p>

        <note>
          If you are not running on localhost you will need to configure
          the application accordingly.
        </note>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Simal REST</title>

        <p>
          Simal-rest provides a REST interface to the registry.
          <code>simal-webapp-VERSION.war</code>
          into your chosen servlet container and point your browser at
          http://localhost:PORT/simal-rest-VERSION
        </p>

        <p>Then point your browser at http://localhost:8080</p>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Simal-core</title>

        <p>
          Simal-core provides a command line interface to the
          repository. It is intended to be self documenting. Run the
          following command to see the documentation:
        </p>

        <source>
  java -cp
    simal-core-0.2-jar-with-dependencies.jar
    uk.ac.osswatch.simal.Simal -h
          </source>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Getting help</title>

      <p>
        Our documentation is minimal at present. If you can't find the
        information you need on this site please search our user mailing
        list
        <a href="ext:simal/userList">archives</a>
        . If you are still lost then join us on our
        <a href="ext:simal/userList">user mailing list</a>
        where we will be glad to answer your questions.
      </p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
